so I would like to go on with our day
today and to announce the next speaker
that we will have with us animation
madness argh again that you already saw
before on stage and the panel is
moderated by under grace falter and also
probably also on the flyer that we have
another name silvano mu Java in a
supposed to be on our panel but
unfortunately due also to really
difficult visa regulation we were not
able to have him here with us and also
because we needed to provide the
insurance that has a small organization
without fixed funded we were not able so
again we agree with Silvano's that he
could be here in spirit with us and we
also prepare a video about his case that
is also really important because it's
related to torture in Zimbabwe and we
asked a bank news Algar to speak about
him so in a sense we will be a bit with
us even if he is not and by the way I
also wanted to say that at the moment is
in residency at the University of
Manchester so if you are interested in
this case is totally up for speaking
about that so so for interviews so he
totally told me that we would be happy
to speak with people if you are
interested to contact him so in a sense
is not here but I also hope that perhaps
in the future or other organization in
Berlin would have the possibility to
invite him and now we go on with our
panel and I would say I would like first
of all to introduce the panel through a
video because as we mentioned before the
17 of May chess remaining we work free
after seven years of prison detention
and this is really an important moment
so since initially she was supposed to
serve 35 years since
reason and for that especially here in
Berlin we want to thank a lot to the
Chelsea Manning initiative Berlin for
their work they did since 2011 until now
that was really a work with a lot of
passion a lot of effort and I think that
also from the disruption lab I want to
give really special thank because
they've been with us really for men
events doing a wonderful work so I
really would like to thank all together
the Chelsea Manning initiative Berlin
and so because of that I think this
panel should start with the video that
the initiative prepared especially for
this location of celebration of Chelsea
and before also watching the video I
would like to announce the moderator of
the panel and a great falter that is the
chair of the wizard global network if
I'll also the cooperation partner of
this event and the Annegret from 1999 to
2014 was a member of the jury bestowing
the German whistleblower award and among
the winners are indeed Chelsea Manning
in 2011 it was knodel in 2013 Brandon
Bryant in 2015 and I'm also really happy
to say that since Brandon was here with
us that our very first event in April in
2015 and so I also want to thank a lot
of the whistleblower Network a foul
because they do a really important job
in Germany for advocacy and protection
and the knowledge dissemination about
whistleblowing and I also speak a lot
about the case of whistleblowers in
Germany that are also not so well known
international as the one that everybody
always mentioned so they do also really
an important job so I would like to
thank them too
so now we go down on stage we will start
with the video by the Chelsea Manning
initiative and then we will have the
people on stage and for the questions
will John Kiriakou will also come back
on stage and do the final rounds with
the public so thanks a lot again for
staying longer year and the please let's
show the video thank you turn down the
lights please
today today before I learned that
Washington never told a lie I learned
the soldiers told I mean you're homeless
everything you not easy for a person in
what healthy by this nobody my sister
jean-yves Danny Bennett or the back of a
helical yeah you will now see the same
anatomical class and 2002 economy
everything else is tiata or in the
policemen are my friends I learned that
justice never and I learned that
murderers die for the crime beautiful
make a mistake somehow he had to join he
had been tried to tell the people
measures to any country or to anywhere
to any organization and he it is not for
himself not for his own father
yeah he did this because he think this
is it is long to public yeah
give Yadav um the human factors
potentially broke is abuse China finder
to forgiveness from God even posits a
German identity channel
mentioned here gajeel Museum time at
Lana's pattern for outside for me that's
why give it imagine
you not a devi kannada carbonyl McKean
and von Karman would invite from ip3
important hotel or the Buddha of my
later time very cozy here was
or Marilyn
and we're here to support breath any
trials to try - three of the creatures
/ classify every minute information that
comes out of this government long-headed
time to both slide through random and
even helping us do that and I create
random American Europe
we need free Bradley Manning because to
extend us free set us free and solve our
line if the world free with the truth
and we need to listen
[Applause]
[Music]
you know helping even the United States
for a process in our country by the
smoke monkey noises to show me
he's got you they need orthography
responsible Connie
everything else is Giada so try he
hasn't tried to sell this information to
any country or to anywhere to any
organization and he it is not for
himself not for his own father
Yahoo this is because he thinks this is
it is belong to puzzle yeah he senator
[Applause]
[Music]
subjective treatment describes 183
strength yeah
okay now yeah keep them in one line
people keep coming online as for Chelsea
needs to go a little bit write them down
a nice week pay attention people you're
going to be here forever dhts go write a
little bit to my right stage right
[Music]
here's
[Applause]
really bright yes John John Kiriakou
would you please oh good so I have been
asked to say a few words about Chelsea
Manning to start out with and I wonder
whether all of you have read his
statement which was just now published
on the website of his legal team have
you read his statement otherwise I would
very quickly read it out to you that
okay okay so I will so that is the
statement of Chelsea Manning upon her
upcoming release from present for the
first time I can see a future for myself
as Chelsea
I can imagine surviving and living as
the person who I am and can finally be
in the outside world freedom used to be
something that I dreamed of but never
allowed myself to fully imagine now
freedom is something that I will again
experience with friends and loved ones
after nearly seven years of bars and
Salmond of periods of solitary
confinement and of my health care and
autonomy restricted including thorough
routinely forced haircuts she lived as a
transgender female in an all-male
present and I'm forever grateful to the
people who kept me alive President Obama
my legal team and countless supporters I
watched the world change from inside
prison walls and through the letters
that I have received from veterans trans
young people parents politicians and
artists my spirits were lifted in dark
times reading of their support sharing
in their triumphs and helping them
through challenges of their own I hope
to take the lessons that I have learned
the love that I have been given and the
hope that I have to work toward me to
work toward making life better for
others so that's what she wrote as of
May 9th few days ago and so what we saw
off in this video we're snapshots
basically and it's once again it was our
friend Nadine who did it and I too want
to thank you very much for her
steadiness and kindness and the
snapshots that come to my mind are
basically three when I hear the name
Chelsea Manning and it's the Colet it's
the Collateral Murder video
it's the unlawful pre-trial pretrial
treatment in prison and it's the
Espionage Act the Collateral Murder
video killing civilians non-combatants
like in the video game a helicopter crew
I mean you probably on all know the
video calling calling killing engagement
it's also this incredibly violent and
brutal language and all that under the
oversight of their superiors it's not
just
it's not just a helicopter crew doing
that but they are in constant contact
with their superiors and it's clearly a
crime it's an it's against international
law on the Geneva Convention and once
again like in John's case only Chelsea
Manning was prosecuted for that and
nobody else and no one from the
helicopter crew so the second thing I
remember is the unlawful cruel
confinement in the Quantico present his
attorney David Coombs had said he was
almost gone at that time and I think the
condition the conditions there are best
described by Graham Nash in a song he
said he sang locked up in a white room
underneath the glaring light every five
minutes they're asking me if I'm all
right
locked up in a white room naked as the
day I was born
24 bright light 24 all alone and all
legal experts were agreed that this was
an unusual cruel treatment before any
trial and the goal and thinking about
the goal why they were so terribly cool
with bread with Chelsea for one thing of
course they wanted to set an example
they wanted to intimidate other
whistleblowers and they were pretty
successful I guess with that and there
one could also assumed that they were
pressuring Chelsea to testify against
WikiLeaks and
so that they could file charges against
him and what they now do by the way I
think you all heard about the charges
that the State Department that the
Department of Justice is supposed to
bring forward soon and indict in Julian
under the Espionage Act - and also some
other charges it's also theft theft of
government of government belongs
whatever so the third thing I the third
thing I am thinking of is the Espionage
Act and it is important to realize that
Chelsea Manning was the first to be not
only indicted but also convicted under
the Espionage Act and that means and the
major points about that are there is no
public interest defense possible no
exonerating arguments like the motives
and intentions of a whistleblower and
whether he caused harm or damage or not
played no role none of the documents
that Chelsea published resulted in
personal or military strategical
strategic harm and the Center for
Constitutional Rights as well as
Ellsberg very early in the 1970s of the
year published the Pentagon Papers it
claimed that this right was
unconstructive law was unconstitutional
being applied to whistleblowers and they
and right now Chelsea from all that I
know and I'm informed about Chelsea is
going to challenge the constitutionality
of the Espionage Act before right now
before the upload at the Appalachian
court and
after that I think everybody is has
decided to proceed to the Supreme Court
so that is the state of the art right
now Chelsea has been commuted his
sentence of Chelsea has been commuted he
wasn't pardoned he was commuted it was
commuted and that is probably also due
to an outpouring of support from the
public over her mistreatment in prison
and they what I learned from the from
the website of her legal team is that he
will go on fighting in her appeal to
clear her name to clear her name
right now Chelsea is not being ready for
interviews the legal team will answer
interviews and I there's a few weeks ago
I talked to her former attorney David
Coombs and he said if I if anybody wants
an interview they have to turn to her
agent so obviously there are so many
people who want to talk to her that she
needs somebody to handle that for her I
now introduce have the honor to
introduce the panel and it's my very
pleasure to present to fabulous one
fabulous with Laura and both of them
distinguished speakers and it first of
for the first to speak is any muscle
sitting next to me here Andy Marshall
was an intelligence officer for the UK
security service mi5 before resigning to
help blow the whistle on the primes and
in competences of the British spy agency
agencies she is now a writer medium
pundit and international public speaker
on issues like
war on terrorism on whistleblower
because of the ways of whistleblowing on
drugs and on the internet and she's also
a member of the Sam Adams Association
Annie is there anything you're going to
speak about the secrecy laws in the UK
is there and is anything comparable to
the Espionage Act yes in fact I'm going
to you'll probably gather I'm British
from my accident and I'm going to blush
yet again I've been blushing a lot this
year since or ever since last year with
the brexit vote now I'm going to blush
again because in fact I think it was the
UK that gave the world the notion of
such laws as the Espionage Act 1917 in
the United States so Britain once again
set a wonderful example because in 1911
they produced the first Official Secrets
Act which was put in place before the
First World War
to try and root out German spies sorry
Germany assessment put them on trial and
shoot them if necessary now this law is
stayed in place it is still there to
prosecute traitors and in fact we've had
a number of traitors throughout the 20th
century most notably the Cambridge spy
ring which has urges Philby MacLean and
a few others who were establishment
figures who betrayed the country
egregiously for decades and yet all of
them somehow magically were allowed to
slip away to Russia their establishment
however if you're a whistleblower
the treatment is somewhat harsher so we
have the 1911 act and it was upgraded a
couple of times in the 1920s and 1930s
but then there are a series of
whistleblowing cases in the 1980s most
notably the very notorious book called
spy catcher written by a disgruntled
former senior mi5 officer called Peter
Wright and because of all these spies
scandals in the 1980's the Sacher
government at the time decided to
upgrade the Official Secrets Act to
specifically bar whistleblowing and that
became known as the 1989 Act
and under that act it says that anyone
who is or has been an intelligence
officer for any of the three key spy
agencies in the UK and who speaks to
anyone outside that agency automatically
faces two years in prison because
they've blown the whistle they've
disclosed information they shouldn't
have and there is no defense
there is no Public Interest defense
there is no opportunity to put in front
of a jury of your peers why you did what
you did and the evidence you are allowed
to present about your disclosures is
severely limited so it's a very
one-sided Act and I'm now going to just
move on a little bit to some personal
reminiscences before bringing the
current legislation that they are
proposing in the UK which is getting
worse and worse and worse in the face of
more whistleblowers just to sort of fill
you in on quite how bad it is in the UK
and I have a sense that where the UK
leads and they did in 1911 the rest of
the world begins to follow and I say
that with knowledge because this year as
well on the first January we had a new
law put in place called the
investigatory powers act and this
legalized what we've previously
illegally done by our snooping agency
GCHQ for the last 17 years this is put
in the most draconian sweeping new
surveillance powers including metadata
bulk hacking
data collection and that applies not
just to the UK but they will use it
against everyone across Europe as well
by the way and this law went in against
huge opposition and yet it was still
forced in and now we're seeing that
those well-known Zipit liberal
democracies such as Russia and China are
now beginning also to copy the UK new
legislation they're saying well if the
UK can do it what's wrong with that
let's do it ourselves so I'm sure that
any new secrecy legislation the UK
brings in will also be copied by other
countries both our allies and our
notional adversary's but first of all I
just want to say
it's wonderful to finally get a chance
to meet John Kiriakou as an intelligence
whistleblower of 20 years standing now
got it so old I can't believe it's 20
years ago that we ended up blowing the
whistle because of that I've been very
very interested in following every
subsequent whistleblower case of course
I follow John's case with interest and
with great concern so I just want to pay
tribute to his courage fortitude then
and also for his continuing courage for
what he's doing now so please give him a
round of applause Annegret mentioned the
Sam Adams associates and this is a loose
affiliation of whistle blows from around
the world from the intelligence the
military in the diplomatic corps and
every year were given award to those who
display integrity in intelligence and
last year we gave that award to John and
I think I can't it was very very well
deserved but it was interesting as well
to listen to what he was saying earlier
because it brought back a lot of
memories for me because back in the
1990s we probably started around the
same time actually not intelligence
careers but mine was much shorter back
in the 1990s I was recruited to work for
mi5 which is the UK domestic security
service and I was there only for six
years and I was there in it's only
marginally ethical decade in its hundred
year existence I know it's also there
that I met a man who became my partner
as well as my colleague my former
partner a man called David Shayler
and after only six years we've seen so
many things going wrong but again we
felt compelled to speak out about them
we had tried to raise our concerns
worried on the inside and we were
repeatedly told do not rock the boat and
just follow orders so after six years of
this we resigned and we went public and
it was a whole range of different things
that caused concern for us including
files on our government ministers files
and hundreds of thousands of our fellow
citizens for their political activism
illegal telephone taps IRA bombs that
could and should have been prevented
going off on UK streets and then mi5
crucially lying to the government to
cover
their mistakes there's a case of two
innocent students going to prison when
mi5 had evidence of their innocence and
it culminated in an illegal
assassination plot against Colonel
Gaddafi of Libya in 1996 where mi6 are
sort of James Bond wing of British
intelligence what they like to think so
anyway
where mi6 had funded a branch of
al-qaeda at that time known to be our
terrorist enemies even in 1996 mi6 had
funded these people to try and
assassinate Gaddafi and the operation
was illegal under UK law because they
didn't get the prior written permission
of their political master and it went
wrong because Gaddafi obviously survived
to be assassinated another day in 2011
but innocent people died so at this
point we felt compelled to try and do
something about this so as I said we
resigned we went public and we
preemptively went on the run around
Europe to avoid automatic arrest under
the draconian terms of the 1989 Official
Secrets Act so we literally had one
month on the run around Europe we then
had another year living in hiding in a
remote and very primitive French
farmhouse and then David was arrested
because the British tried to extradite
him from France where he'd taken refuge
to take him back to the UK to stand
trial under the Official Secrets Act and
we're in Paris at that time talking from
journalists and he just disappeared he
was snatched off the street and the
first I knew of his arrest was when I
had a knock on the hotel door from the
French security service the DST at the
time and they said we have Monsieur
Shaila and I said well we know is he
under arrest no no we're just taking the
way for questioning and I asked if I
could see him they said no and that was
the last I saw of him for almost two
months he disappeared into the French
prison system and even his lawyers
couldn't track him down for 72 hours and
when they eventually did track him down
only the lawyers were allowed to see him
because the French had been told by the
British that he was a traitor a super
spy selling secrets to enemy powers so
they put him under very stringent
secrecy laws effectively almost solitary
confinement and I wasn't allowed to see
him and it's only after the paperwork
finally emerged from the British
government requesting his extradition
after two months but they realized what
they had in their prison cell with a
whistleblower not a traitor and under
French law you cannot be extradited for
whistleblowing the creditors deemed was
deemed at the time to be a political act
so he was released and that was fabulous
and in fact we had taken prior legal
advice before we went on the run of
which country would be best to hide in
and ironically back in 1997 we were told
France will be good because they protect
whistleblowers and so with the USA and
he's talking what the hell happened
there luckily we settled on France
because it was easier to get a bit
closer to the UK so he was released and
we had another two years living in Paris
relatively free although he could not
leave France because if he went to any
other European country at that point he
too would face another extradition
request and probably would have been
extradited but he went back in the year
2000 to face trial to say this is what I
said I stand by it
I want it read into the public record I
want my day in court to justify what I
did so you went back voluntarily and of
course was immediately arrested when he
set foot on UK soil and we thought the
trial would be fairly rapid I mean you
know everything had happened almost
three years ago
surely the Metropolitan Police are
concluded their investigation after
three years right instead we were
dragged through a whole series of
pretrial hearings which were designed to
inhibit increasingly what he was
actually finally allowed to say during
his trial and this went on for over two
years so by the time he was able to
stand up in front of a jury of his peers
he was not allowed to say why he'd done
what he'd done he was not allowed to use
a public interest defense and in fact he
wasn't allowed to ask any questions
without the prosecuting
lawyer vetting them ahead of time and
crossing them all out it was a kangaroo
court and some of it was conducted in
secret - so inevitably he was convicted
and he was facing three charges each
carrying two years in prison
however the only time either of in this
whole legal process were ever allowed to
say anything about why we had done what
we done ironically was after his
conviction but before his sentencing
when rather stupidly I talked myself
into giving what was known as a
mitigation plea so I could explain our
reasons I could explain what had
happened and the judge at that point
just gave him six months instead of six
years so that was a good issue result
having said that though there is also
the reputational rape that happened in
the newspapers and the media after his
conviction so the judge also said in his
final official ruling he accepted that
Shailja had done what he'd done in what
he thought was the public interest not
that that was a legal defense that there
was no financial motivation and that no
agent lives had ever been put at risk
through his whistleblowing and yet the
headlines on all and newspapers the next
day said precisely the opposite Shane
Lascelles agent lives down the river for
money as I think where the hell did that
come from I was sitting in the courtroom
watching the journalists write down the
judges words which it makes you we can
just speculate along very paranoid and
interesting lines about quite how much
control the spies can exert over our
wonderful Free Press so David went to
prison again he'd spent four months in
prison in Paris in a very primitive and
draconian prison which has now been shut
down on humanitarian grounds by the way
and then he was sent to prison in the UK
now he was a low security risk
he should have immediately gone to a low
security prison oh no they took almost a
month to decide on what his official
category would be and in that month he
was put in the notorious Belmarsh prison
which is the highest security prison in
the UK
housing terrorists crime lords all the
rest of it and he was day under physical
threat and he was very stressed about it
and I said well how did you try and get
these the threats to back off and again
you know thinking hearing what John was
saying brought back a lot of memories of
what David would told me and he said
there was one point where there's some
huge guy came up to him and tried to
push him off the one public phone he was
allowed to use and he put around this
rumor that he could kill with his bare
hands because that was his training in
li5 which is absolutely not the case by
the way and I can't do that either
I promise and this huge guy just backed
off in subject terror but it's an
incredibly stressful thing to go through
I mean the whole case will start finish
went for seven years from when we took
the decision in 1996 to when he was
finally a free man who had paid his
so-called debt to society and in those
years in the media you are pilloried as
a traitor or you are supported as a hero
and it's a very difficult dichotomy to
live with as an individual I think and
in fact unfortunately I think that
stress did get to him
we separated over ten years ago now and
he's a happily a scholar in his new life
as an reincarnation of Jesus Christ I
think which I know sounds funny but if
you think this guy has such a sharp
brain here's such good officer such a
good man and this is what living with
those years of stress can do to someone
so that's the price that whistle blows
pay and I know many other whistle blows
you have been destroyed either
financially or psychologically and by
what they go through and it's wonderful
see some of us still help though some of
us still thriving and John obviously
still very much kicking butt which is
what we all need to do so that was the
case then I just want to conclude with a
few remarks about what's going on in the
UK now because I've been watching in
horror at what is mound called the war
on whistleblowers in the USA you know
there's overuse of this bogus law the
Espionage Act illegally to prosecute
people who are blowing the whistle
but the UK is also trying to reform its
Official Secrets laws so we have the old
osa in 1911 for traitors
osa 1989 for whistle blows now they're
getting their knickers in a twist in the
British government about loosing parent
increasing threat of the insider threat
like a whistle blows and organizations
like WikiLeaks which publish those
disclosures so they are reviewing all
these old laws and they come up with
some wonderfully stupid proposals first
of all they're going to clump the early
Official Secrets Act into something new
called the Espionage Act strangely
enough I wonder where they got that idea
from and then for the whistleblowing
they're going to create a new law called
the Disclosure Act now this will apply
to whistle blows and raise the prison
tariffs from 2 years to 14 this will
also mean that organizations that help
disclosure such as the media and one
thinks particularly probably they're
thinking along the lines of WikiLeaks
can also be prosecuted and face the same
tariffs and also they're going to expand
it at the moment to the Official Secrets
Act only apply to British citizens
however they're going to expand it now
to any national who facilitates the
publication of official secret Official
Secrets so of course again they're
thinking Julian Assange one presumes and
finally for example I'm a former
intelligence officer if I go out and
talk about stuff that is already in the
public domain such as a lot of very
detailed information in my old books
that was cleared by mi5 or other
information that I learn from other
whistle blows such as John Kerry a coup
or any of the other Sam Adams
whistleblowers they want to criminalize
me again by taking away what is known as
the pub of the public domain defense ie
that information is already in the
public domain for anyone should be able
to talk about it and they are saying now
or proposing that if I do that or if
John talks about something I discuss
any other UK with four blow does that
then we are in a situation where because
we're serving or former intelligence
officers we are amplifying the gravitas
of repeating that information giving it
credibility so they're going to try and
take away that defense for me and others
as well so this is sliding precipitously
down an incredibly dangerous half and my
big fear is that other European
countries particularly will no doubt
start to follow as they have already
started to follow with the investor
powers act the snoopers Charter and it's
not just Russia and China that have
picked up on that countries like Germany
and Norway Norway are also following
suit
so Britain unfortunately is blundering
again down diametrically wrong paths
that it should be going and many of us
in the UK have been advocating for years
there should be a formal whistleblowing
channel for those with meaningful
ethical concerns coming out of central
government the intelligence agencies the
military the diplomatic corps where they
can go without jeopardizing not only
their professional life but their
liberty with the assumption and trust
that what they disclose will be properly
investigated and if crimes have indeed
been committed those criminals will be
held to account not the whistleblower
and I would suggest just to conclude
that that would be the most obvious
win-win situation that any intelligence
agency or any government could possibly
suggest because you avoid the
whistleblowing scandal you don't have
inquiries you don't have hearings and
after the event you don't have the press
building itself up into a media frenzy
and the spies loads that but also the
whistleblower doesn't have to turn their
lives inside out upside down go through
prison and deal with that trauma so if
if they suggest in Germany some sort of
equivalent Official Secrets Act please
push back rally activate fight it and
suggest the alternative the win-win
scenario because it will help everyone
it will save the whistleblower it will
improve the works of the spy agencies
and it will allow them therefore to
protect all of us much better thank you
[Applause]
thank you so much Annie and he may I ask
a quick question what about the public
what about the general public remember
slowed and he said it's not me who
decides how much freedom we are trading
in for security he wanted to inform the
public he wanted to have a democratic
discourse going on and the solution that
you have proposed it excludes that and I
think one should think twice about that
well I'm suggesting actually that if
there is a proper channel for potential
whistleblowers to go down and they do
disclose crime and there is a proper
investigation and there a trial then of
course that informations going to come
out but via the trial rather than via a
blaze of publicity is probably not
perfect but it's either that will more
whistle blows coming out more
whistleblowers
risking their lives in many cases and
you know ruining their futures and for
going to prison so I think you know that
would be good first step and put the
whole concept of whistleblowing
very much in the public consciousness
again but give it legal backing or maybe
to try to to strengthen the
possibilities of defense in the public
interest
like the European Council proposed later
predatory to whoever private discussion
here and I'm now I have the pleasure to
introduce Magnus out actually was
introduced already and so I say maybe
for those who came a little later let me
just mention that Magnus AG is a
berlin-based
international human rights and freedom
of expression advocate he works at free
news an international civil society
organization defending and promoting the
right to artistic freedom and work
freedom worldwide
prior to joining cream
in 2015 Magnus spent five years with a
committee committee to protect
journalists in New York and right now
here he is going to speak about why art
is not a crime and he is going to speak
about free muse and how they defend
artistic freedom and before doing that
he told me he was going to change hats
and he will now introduce he'll Vanna
Smith Silva and who is and I regret and
I think that Jana has already said that
that he couldn't come and so a madness
is going to speak with his head on now
yeah so I'm back again but yeah and I
really wish to Sylvanas could be here I
think you would have loved this I talked
to him earlier this this week he says hi
and thank you very much to Chiana for
her work and the whole team's of getting
him here and giving the opportunity to
at least show show this video and I
Pajama asked me to introduce a my Mets
Alana's first time a couple years ago in
Harare Zimbabwe and was so impressed
with his work and have stayed in touch
with him he is described himself as a
performing arts activist and I don't go
into too many details about him because
he does a much better job about
explaining his own project in in this
video but I thought they may be a bit of
a background on Zimbabwe might be
helpful since it's not top of mind for
everyone here and they have a few slight
first of all here is same Bob them and I
wanted to ask you guys how many here are
37 years old or younger finish your
hands a lot of hands and can you
remember or do you know who was
president when oh yeah when you use our
37 were born so in 1980 in your
respective countries anyone remember
just there here's the slide the next one
that kind of gives you an idea about the
situation in Zimbabwe Robert Mugabe he
was president or he was Prime Minister
in 1980 he won an election in 1979 the
first free election in - Bob way after
they gained independence from it from
the United Kingdom he was part of the
liberation movement he merged that into
a presidency a few years later as we see
other people do these days and then he
stayed in power ever since and he has a
stronghold of power and there's been
some elections with questionable results
there's very limited freedoms to talk
about these things there's a state-owned
press for the most part and I just to
really appreciate what this Cervantes is
doing it's important to understand how
that has dominated society for a
generation right to think of not having
had anyone else as head of state and not
seeing any alternative you can imagine
like expressing yourself about these
things are very very tricky it would be
like having Margaret Thatcher still in
power yeah and just some contact on what
he's done like you said he introduced
these land reforms among other things
probably what he's most famous for
internationally because Zimbabwe when it
was relatio there's a lot of white
farmers that owned huge partial and made
a lot of money but also produced a lot
of goods and these land reforms were
highly controversial and they made all
the or not all but a significant part of
the white farmers leave and then the
farms were taken over by by black
Zimbabweans who didn't have the resource
or didn't manage to keep the same level
of the productivity so what was once
known as the breadbasket of the region
it's a very fertile area is now or has
had trouble even feeding its own
population and maybe with the next slide
one of the things that that has come
across it this hyperinflation I don't
know if you remember 2008 they had
insane inflation I think I have
an inflation rate for November mid
November 2008 the inflation rate was 79
billion percent you can imagine like
this is a picture of course of a guy
stopping Billy and you could not use
your money you couldn't get a piece of
bread for the build with the infinite
amount of zeros on it
it is complete direct economy and Lukas
managed to stay in power throughout this
and by repressing any kind of opposition
having very like have a new constitution
that is actually fairly well written
from 2013 and like the words are good
but guaranteeing freedom of expression
the right to artistic freedom which
affects the vanos media right but then
you have a censorship law you have it
censorship board you have practices by
the police but they target journalists
or artist and activist jailing them and
kind of a real sense of insecurity and a
lot of self-censorship about around
everyone that tried to express anything
so that's that's the quick run-through
of sandpaper and then I think if we can
show the video of this Alanis you'll see
how cool he is
my name is savannas motorola I'm a
performing arts activist Taren Zimbabwe
yes a little give you a little bit of
background so that you are in the clear
picture um our country Zimbabwe is with
14 million citizens they've been rode by
one president since 1980 until today we
only have what one television station
that is catering for 14 million citizens
and they have lost confidence in terms
of receiving a propaganda that is being
turned out on that TV station so the
theater is actually become the other
alternative that is available for people
to access information
lastly yeah I decided to actually take
my theatre from the traditional theatre
and bringing it to the ground what
others would call hit and run theatre
others would want to call it guerrilla
theater or just know mostly theatre what
I've been doing since last year is the
president openly come up in the open
inside the country lost the 15 billion
the United States dollars of German
revenue and Noah was arrested not even a
single investigation all done into this
game then I started to say the pediment
is silent about this issue how basic in
actually be part and parcel of this
whole process and then I created the
pleasure of state roads missing diamonds
whereby are after creating the plate was
a shock thing that I just wanted to do
quickly and then make sure that I do it
in front of development
MPs get the message so that admitted a
debate about this issue inside the hotel
so when I actually performed and I was
arrested it also brought a lot of
attention to the suburban community to
say I think we we need to start talking
about this issue and then the MPS that
are deliberating the issue in Parliament
the same day that I was arrested theatre
is absolutely a catalyst of absolute
provoking the bed from the
parliamentarians the citizens themselves
but what I got was really straight and
Vine
the police office has the central
intelligence when they arrested me they
turned me with the disappearance like
what it happened to a colleague of mine
who went missing on the ninth day of
March 2015 and he hasn't been found
until today so I thought it was like one
of the the things that they always do to
say that they would actually want to
stop me
I started receiving strange phone calls
I was being followed at times but I
thought I its natural him mainly when
you're actually operating in him in an
environment led to babble then on 13
September I'm in the middle of the night
they came they knocked down the door
they possibly took me um they went with
me some 40 kilometers outside our alley
they tortured me
I'm the at the end they injected me with
an unknown substance
I stayed in hospital for about four
weeks and after that I was operated on
my stomach was I was actually being like
stumped on my stomach so they wanted to
construct my mine in this time and after
that like this there was a lot of fear
that was put in citizens in terms of
what had happened to me then I said to
myself when I get out of hospital how
best can I make sure that I do not
become part and parcel of the people
while for the third thing and then they
ran away so I created this situation
whereby I started putting on mud on
myself moving in town we're going
towards Parliament we attended like a
huge following that was following me and
when I reached the Parliament I started
performing in front of the Parliament
MPs came they watched the play and when
like the police only duty to arrest me
the citizens they stood with me and say
no you're not done anything is
absolutely highlighting the problems
that are happening in this country so it
was like one of the things that I could
say it motivate it gives me that
motivation to say the people like they
are so interested in what is happening
and if they are also willing to be part
and parcel of this thing from to say we
need to like fight for freedom of
information we need like to fight for
freedom of expression and then lastly I
did another performance
all this time we were like 400 um human
rights activists were arrested randomly
so there was nothing that was being done
in actually bringing them out they just
arrested and taken to court and remanded
in custody it was like three weeks now
yet they were still inside the custodian
then I said the entries are silent again
against this issue the minister
responsible for justice is silent
against this issue how then do I
actually contribute so that is the bed
again starts happening about these
people we've been away arrested and then
I put myself in prison grab leg irons
and end chains I started like moving
again in town going towards Parliament
it's got so much in terms of Attraction
that even the police when they send to
Central Intelligence of his officers
later arrested me they couldn't because
the MPs we're watching if the place was
watching so it was one of the ways that
we have actually tried to use to make
sure that we actually reach the people
as many as we can to hide behind numbers
it has good consequences I am now
disabled I am now living separately from
my family I am now a fellow at
University of Manchester cases of the
artistic protection funds creative
dissent is one of the ways for actually
for me to actually believe that we can
do more in terms of using ads to change
the issues that are happening in the
world globe is using the ads for
achieving change in the world thank you
[Applause]
so madness how do you or does your
organization how does free muse work on
cases like that yes sir my third hat of
the night that now it's my day job
working for a previous defending the
right to artistic freedom and we have
the privilege of course once in order to
work with wonderful people like
Silvano's and then when I knew him
because we did a workshop in Harare
about the like for a UN record we were
doing and then they stayed in touch with
him and followed in on Facebook he's
very active on social media I would
definitely encourage you to find him and
and then one day he texted me from his
hospital that like the day after he was
tortured and health for like 72 hours or
something and then he was in hospital
and he texted me and said this happened
and then we reached out to context is of
course with small organization based in
Copenhagen and I'm here and we don't
have anyone in Zimbabwe but we have a
network of other activists and
organizations at least on the continent
and someone Zimbabwe and he's in
Manchester now and we can make some
credit connected some people and vouched
for him being a real activist doing this
kind of work is so some other
organizations with more funds could
support him financially and then not to
me the Arctic's Protection Fund set this
made this set up with the Manchester
University where he is now for a year in
this residency and then then we'll see
but how that ties into all our work I
thought I would just run through some of
our strategy and the findings we have as
an organization defending the right to
artistic freedom and so um maybe the
first slide is fairly self-explanatory
let me defend the right to artistic
freedom of your human rights
organization that comes from the human
rights declaration and under the right
to freedom of expression and cultural
rights of course artists and audiences
very important has the right to express
themselves artistically
and when Tatyana asked me to do do this
part of it I kind of try to think about
the concept of truth in relation to the
arts and we don't say that the art that
it's true what we are like we defend art
because we think art is important and
out has a value in itself so also a
catalyst would change but not
necessarily and who knows and who's to
judge what piece of art today will have
an effect down the line right but I I
went back to this old quote by a Picasso
I know some of you might have seen it I
butchered a little only to the shortest
sentence like it's part of a sentence
but art is a lie that makes us realize
the truth and I really appreciate that
and I from my perspective and our work
and kind of leave it at that right we
need the arts it's hard to pinpoint
exactly for what and does it change
things does it not but what we need it
and it makes us realize things about the
world we live in so that's why I'm very
happy and privileged to do this kind of
work that we do and aside for some
muscle homage of course work with a
bunch of other artists and I wanted to
show a quick video that kind of gives
you a an idea of the range of people we
work with this band is desired right
I was stopped over there my car was
blocked no he can't shoot me because of
the back in the drawing they were
kidnapped and taken to the victors dole
Food Company want to stop that story
from red shouts they can torture you
they can kill you there's a sensor
should practice by the state whenever
you go anywhere my work was withdrawn
last minute I spent 11 years energy for
the first time there's been a gathering
like this we're bringing together 50
artists from around the world they've
suffered enormous Lee for their work
there are people who've been in exile
they've had death threat in order to
carry on their work we've overcome these
obstacles and kept on going it's an
extraordinary tribute to their
creativeness that's what so great about
this conference you see all these brave
people who risked everything events like
this are creating networks that can
support even better likes pressing
ourselves is how the world will change
the most dangerous thing is silence when
there's no conflict when nobody's put in
jail
it means that the human spirit is dead
yes that's some of the people we work
with and then my next slide is very
simple it's always like should I put it
together but how we work as many many
other human rights organizations we do a
lot of put a lot of energy and research
trying to figure out what is happening
on the ground around the world in our
own societies and other societies and
getting that and verifying that is of
course tremendously difficult then we do
campaigning can be everything from the
very specific we want this artist
released immediately to the broader
advocacy strategies of getting a new UN
process implemented or changing a law on
a country and then our third pillar is
kind of the network and why I'm here to
engage more people to help with this and
to share information share knowledge and
I really appreciate the disruption
network lab approach and this bringing
for example whistleblowers and it won't
claim to be an artist but the artistic
perspective into the same room and have
this conversation I think is really
great and wonderful and so going back to
the research just to give you an idea of
how we see the world this is our
statistics for 2016 every we can't like
every day we register new cases and
every year we do an annual report called
a learner's let we documented the three
killings in 2016 to artistic ducted 16
attacked 84 artists imprisoned 43
persecutions 40 persecutions or threats
and 840 acts of censorship and this is
we use the cliched tip of the iceberg as
it's very hard to verify so I'm sure
there's cases in particular censorship
cases is toast impossible to count but
but we try but I'm sure there's others
and just to dive in a little bit and on
what kind of cases now you know Sylvanas
but some of the other cases we see for
example these guys through five the
Tibetan musician Tibetan monks singing
about a free Tibet or that about the
Dalai Lama very the lyrics I've seen
very peaceful and non control
or to an ordinary ear but to the Chinese
state that is something that I can lend
you up to like nine years in prison for
this ridiculous charge of seditious lis
splitting the state so there's many
legal regimes around the world that have
weird judges against good people yeah
these guys are serving between three and
a half and nine years in prison and it's
again one of those cases was really hard
to figure out are they still in how are
they being treated we do some
awareness-raising
but it's very limited and the Chinese
obviously don't really listen to us even
we have the UN sent a formal request for
information they ignore that as well
another case that I I wanted to
highlight from last year with this
Turkish musician good Sal V's min hand
sorry if I butchered hiddens name I'm
not that good in Turkish he performed a
song about a baby donkey and in the
turkey that is the kind of a term for
calling someone a fool like an insult
but not really works just like a mild
insult he was then subsequently charged
and sentenced to 11 month and 20 days in
prison for insulting president Erdogan
and the funny part about this is that he
didn't mention the name arrogant he
didn't mention anything about president
he was just thinking about a donkey and
it made me think of that Picasso quote
of the little thing little lies that
make us realized the truth right it is
incredible what Chris Denari and how
spin skin T is and how many libel
charges in the charges he put against
all kind of people that criticize him or
it may be even just thing about donkeys
so to zoom out a little bit again we of
course aggregate all this data and these
are the numbers you saw first before I
just changed them into a bar graph and
organized them by violation types so you
have furthest to the left I know it's a
little small killed then abducted the
red dot there in is Silvano's right
because he's in theater and he was
abducted in 2016 then attacked
imprisoned
secured persecute and threatened and
then you see the censorship one going
really high up and it's a bit of an
animal this year because in Ukraine we
saw this ban of 500 Russian films and
they were like specifically named and
then we counted as one act of censorship
if it's a specific art piece that is
banned from another country so that's
why that one is so high censorship is of
course always high and the next chart
it's kind of flipped around so now it's
organized by art form you'll see because
of that Ukraine ban film is obviously
very very high and censorship in general
all across all the platforms music is
the second highest and if you look at
what we like to call that the serious
violations not saying censorship and not
serious but the really like physical
harm or you put in front of a judge one
or another attacker threatened then
music is the the hardest hit art form
and the next slide I just divided the
doubt on on countries and took away the
censorship cases so this again only the
what we call the serious violations and
here you kind of have the usual suspects
when you look at human rights violations
Iran tops with 30 violations in 2016
turkey with 23 Egypt with 18 Nigeria was
a bit of surprise for us and maybe you
can go into that in Q&A if you want to
but we and then Russia and and China or
China and Russia sorry that order so
publishing similar maps with them with
other human rights violations in the
past and just I don't want to skip to
then what we try to do about this and
our approach and I go back to that very
simple slide I had before and down to
kind of the campaign advocacy side of
things now we know this is the situation
that with similar trends in past years
and we see similar trends sentient of
the human rights field and our basic
idea is on a national level we want to
raise the cost of governments of doing
this so if a government in person
someone we want to make sure it's costly
for them
I have no illusions that some
Indian government is going to change his
mind and suddenly oh that was a bad idea
to imprison this artist or this
whistleblower what is going to get
people out is that it's such an
annoyance for the government to have
them in jail if they get met with that
question why is this musician in jail
when they meet with foreign governments
when they turn on the TV or if they go
to social media that is eventually what
is going to change that it's a more
expedient strategy for the government
not people in prison so that's kind of
standard human rights but our approach
on a national level on a global level I
mentioned already we engage a lot with
the Human Rights Council at the UN and
make it's a bit tricky our the Universal
Periodic Review process is some of you
know that it's a process where every
country every member state of the UN is
up for review every four and a half
years so Germany is up ISM Bob way is up
and other of other member states can
critique and have constructive dialogue
around their human rights record so
that's been a good vehicle for us to
address artistic freedom Human Rights
Watch Amnesty will also submit reports
about torture about women's rights about
the whole thing and we then come in with
our reports analyzing what laws and
practices are violating the right to
freedom expression artistic freedom in
that country at a regional level being
based in Europe we engage with the
European Union as much as you can both
on a like the European Member State
should respect the Cystic freedom the
neighboring and enlargement countries is
we see as a way in Turkey for example to
push our message and try to influence
that they use that that as a standard
negotiating with other countries about
becoming a member that you at least
respect human rights freedom of
expression and of course also in
partnership agreements with the third
countries as they call it a new language
so when you have a trade agreement with
Vietnam that there's also some kind of
acknowledgment that Vietnam needs to
respect human rights and freedom of
expression at a cities and institutions
level is kind of lack of a better word
what I call it
we work with these residences and others
so Silvano's for example he's in
Manchester via they are
protection point and there's this icon
city of refuge where cities can kind of
host an artist or journalist or writer
started by Salman Rushdie or like that
whole way when this battle against him
was issued and then finally there's the
artistic and activist community and kind
of you guys and us and all and I think
one of our key missions is to get
everyone on board to collaborate around
these things and make sure there's
solidarity among us so when an artist is
targeted or an activist or whistleblower
somewhere in the world that we
collectively stand up and show
solidarity and raise awareness make sure
they're not forgotten those stories
about being forgotten in prison is of
course something we all we hear a lot
and that's maybe my my last slide just
to go back and be specific this case
with from Iran that is really close to
my heart and two brothers methi's Rajab
Ian and Hussein Rajab Ian maybe as a
musician who sign as a filmmaker they
had this underground day and music
distributor together an online platform
where you can listen to music
traditional Iranian music that the
method my mother's played on his sitar
so not even any lyrics that criticized
the regime or a very profane and in or
anything and these guys were first
detained Mehdi was allegedly tortured
during interrogations and then this was
back in 2013 last year they were then
sentenced first their six years now to
three years in prison for insulting the
sacred at propaganda against the state
and then on June 5 last year they were
put in jail and even present if some of
you know the Iranian prison system
that's a pretty horrific place to be a
lot of political prisoners but also a
lot of drug addicts and drug crimes like
average criminals rough situation to be
in that prison
they've been on a hunger strike several
times to protest their situation
specifically their medical leads and so
I just wanted to finish off with that in
on June 5
been there for years we kind of do a big
push to raise awareness itself to engage
with the Iranian government but but this
is how how governments kind of suppress
artistic freedom and of course it ties
into all kinds of other opposition
voices in Iran being treated the same
way so to kind of round up and conclude
I just want to again this is something
you see over time that governments and
others in the position of power they
want to secure like a single dominant
narrative right and I think that might
be the common denominator for us up here
and artists and other Sarge's and
annoyance to that they are not they
don't fit into one frame they don't stay
the same at the government right they
say the opposite or they say something
third and I think with the rise of
populism and nationalism as we see now
in many places of the world like I am
even more concerned because that is very
much the dominant agenda right is to
define that one narrative who we are we
don't want to respect human rights
because that is a limitation on the will
of the majority right I won I can do
whatever I want kind of logic where the
human rights regime is of course to
protect the rights of the minority but
these populist and nationalist movements
kind of seem to get that wrong so I
think it's important that we do things
like that we share information we
document these cases and go out and get
people out of jail thank
[Applause]
Thank You Magnus and as it is getting
really late and we're a little behind
our schedule I was asked to open the
panel to the flow right away and I would
like to ask you to concentrate a little
on countermeasures of the question what
can we do and maybe some of your
questions questions that years
contribute to that okay so as here right
ahem
oh please run now see first I have to
earlier now I nearly forgot you John
would you please come to this would you
please come here if you're still there
which I hope very much Oh indeed so see
okay so maybe we start out without him
and I see a hand right there in the
middle and maybe we ask one question or
make one comment after the other
relatively short so that one of the two
speakers here can precisely answer them
yes hello hi thank you very much my name
is Gisela I work for a Latin American
NGO called very to the hit Alice I am
Mexican and I just want to thank Marcos
for his intervention because I just want
to be honest this was a bit too white
for me I believe that John's
intervention was good but he was still
speaking of a prison that was less worse
than Afghanistan
whereas in Mexico we have prisons
controlled by drug cartels so I think I
still think it's a position of privilege
I mean this is its in terms of class of
race and gender maybe so I just want to
say that as a comment and then my
particular question regarding that
because it's so much horrible to get
that more than a question I have a come
right so I do actually have a question
how do we make how do we approach this
and I also acknowledge that the British
government
I mean Latin American governments are
going to do what the British government
is doing now in five years so how do we
and I really like your intervention
because of that so how do we address
these problems for my Universalist
perspective without being too white but
just acknowledging that it is a trend
and that power tends to behave the same
in terms of co-opting narratives and
distort perceptions about it so I don't
know whoever wants to respond that I
just felt I needed to say that thank you
I suppose it's the British I should go
get a blush again I suppose this one
faint hope they're the post-breakfast
Britons just going to fade or fake to a
certain extent and stop exerting this
malign influence but then I suppose is
good to then be The Fountainhead of all
things secrecy I don't think the USA is
a particularly good example either I
don't know I mean ever the last decade
or so I've seen I've been encouraged to
see greater independence or sort of
break or a spirit across Latin America
are many issues most notably of course
things like the drug issue or breaking
away from the Western financial hegemony
as well the idea of Brazil getting
involved in the Russian Chinese new
investment bank and things like that so
there is hope but I suppose as always in
Latin America we tend to see America
then trying to meddle and keep control
of what it can see confused to be its
own backyard
rather than sovereign national states
you know after the unrest fermented in
Venezuela a potential coup in Ecuador
that might be brewing what happened in
Brazil so I think actually probably got
more to worry about from America than
Britain but yes I think Britain does set
a very bad track to other countries and
America knows knows they're going to
abuse and you yeah and I maybe want to
take your first point and I really
appreciate about privilege and also use
that to flip it and say
with everything happening with Trump for
example is one of the best comments I
saw a commentary on it was Turkish
journalists telling you as journalists
how they should now try to counter this
right that thick we can learn us white
people in the global North some people
around the world and we're in it
together and we are facing similar
issues right it's not this us and them
kind of logic it is people have gone
through situations with repressive
governments through history and they do
in all parts of the world and if we as a
community that believe in human rights
and these freedoms work together their
sum up like it's idealistic but there's
some hope there please I mean we can't
see you from here so somebody just get
up there back there
okay plea my hi thank you everyone for
the nice presentations my question would
be to - and I think Giselle's comment is
really important
thank you for pointing that out I just
saw a question I'm here I thank you for
the work you've done so far and I was
just wondering if you're doing anything
or do you know anything about therapy or
a support group for the artists were
suffering from also censorship asking
for a friend
yeah I guess it depends on where in the
world and and support group specific for
self-censorship or author censorship
I think groups like us that's what we
work with and one of our big challenges
in our research is to document this how
do you document like all these numbers I
show like you can't say this is one case
of self-censorship of outer censorship
which makes it really hard to deal with
that issue and what we then try to do is
talk to artists on and off the record
get them to describe the
situation when they feel they might fail
sensor of men they might not and often
they don't want to say this on the
record and then if if that is because
they're scared of the police which is in
many states if it's they're scared for
like economic consequences that's
definitely also an aspect of it that is
interesting and very complex if it's cuz
Apple like iTunes has limb that you
can't say [__] in the title on iTunes
right like then your music won't be
published there and that will have a
kind of consequences so it's because
you're afraid of the Chinese regime
coming every other there's a lot of
different issues in that and depending
on where in that the question you are I
think that we could help find someone
that would know more about this
situation but I think it is very country
specific or local how the specific
situation is but as a global
organization we kind of tried to address
this as best we can and work with a lot
of people on this okay are there any
more questions yes back there please so
I have a question for any you talked
about how you wanted to start an
organization that whistleblowers could
go to with their concerns that would
then investigate those concerns but a
lot of whistleblowers talk about how
they've exhausted internal channels and
that didn't work so what would make this
different from other internal channels
and also how would this group we kept
accountable and who would check that
this group was investigating things as
they said that they were doing
absolutely I think I mean this idea is
because of the British setup where there
are intelligence commissioners who have
designed to oversee the intelligence
agencies and have done a particularly
good job but there's also a committee in
Parliament called the Intelligence and
Security Committee which is absolutely
crap it's useless it's had no power
meaningfully for 23 years now but having
something external like Commissioner or
committee but with real investor powers
and who really does their job and of
course they'd only be trusted if they do
that job and it seemed to be done and
there are court cases resulting out of
it
then that I think would be a better path
for both the agencies and also the staff
you know the potential was suppose to go
down because it would be win-win
it doesn't mean everything's brushed
under the carpet it doesn't mean that
those who have committed crimes on the
inside get away with it as happens now
as we all know because there would be
result in court cases if the evidence
were found of course that doesn't
obviate the need for whistle blows if
they feel blocked and it's not working
then of course they're going to get back
to doing that but I think it's always
worth exploring potential other options
because at the moment particularly in
the UK there is what's called a clear
bright line against disclosure you
cannot talk to anyone outside your
agency or you go to prison that's it
there's no defense no nothing the
current review of the Official Secrets
Act has specifically excluded the need
for reintroducing the public interest
defense which was removed in the 89 act
so it's very messy it's increasingly
draconian Britain is the most secretive
intelligence community in any Western
notional democracy they are the most
legally protected of any intelligence
agencies so it's trying to think what
might be acceptable I was talking in
terms of the UK what might be an
acceptable first step I don't think
whistle blows are going to go away I
don't think organisations like WikiLeaks
are going to go away that genie is out
of the bottle technologically so this is
really trying to minimize the damage and
improve the work of the agencies because
lots of good people do go and work there
they want a job that will make a
difference and protect their fellow
citizens and for that initiative to be
stifled or to be corrupted or to be
crushed it's a crying shame I think so
it's really trying to find an avenue to
these people any was their trail against
yours your partner was its public key
yes the trial against David Shayler was
largely public but they would go
in-camera when the prosecutor said we
can't talk about this but what they're
proposing now under the new Official
Secrets Act is entirely secret trials
they're not even reported
I think you said the public will learn
about all that when the thing when the
case comes to trial and do you really
think that given I mean all empirical
evidence is against that that secret
document and given the secrecy the
secretive 'ti of the agencies and that
anything will ever come out and you said
yourself they can if they provide a
channel like that they can it can
prevent getting information into the
public and I think there is information
where the public has a right to know and
so may I ask you as a to constitutional
Patriot as you turn in the home and what
do you think about public whistleblowing
um I I think that whistleblowing should
be public man I comment on the trial
aspect as well
my trial actually was not public I mean
I didn't make it up to trial
I took a plea but in the United States
we have this thing called the cipa the
classified information Protection Act
and so the entire courtroom is cleared
when when I walk in I'm allowed only my
attorneys there's the prosecution the
judge and a clerk and we're not even
allowed to use certain words so there's
a list of words and then substitute
words so if I want to say a classified
word I have to say instead swimming pool
so we intercepted the swimming pool as
the place and and you have to constantly
refer to this list of words so you don't
accidentally say a word that the CIA has
deemed to be classified and then get
another charge on top of what you've
already been charged with add to that as
well during them the Schaller trial the
key story and the reason we went public
was the Gaddafi assassination plot and
this actually made international global
headlines actually and was a big course
filler but there are calls for inquiries
proper public inquiries into what spies
been doing the government denied it blah
blah blah so the six weeks duration of
David's trial this disclosure this story
was banned it was banned under something
called the Public Interest immunity
certificates which is a gagging order by
the British government and this was a
super gagging order so the press could
not even say they were not allowed to
talk about it in case that might
influence the jury even though this had
been headline news for years by that
point particularly in the UK so it was a
little calf caress in the sense that we
weren't allowed to breathe that word
during the trial journalists weren't
allowed to write about that and some of
them actually quite close to it trying
to say in it we are being gagged and was
prison for it but yeah it is Kafka resk
it's frightening watching it in action
this is the experience with the court
martial of Bradley matters Chelsea
Manning I mean it was the public was
literally excluded from most of their of
their trial this is an ongoing theme
actually if I hope you don't mind my
interjecting Chelsea Manning went
through this Tom Drake went through this
Jeffrey sterling in spades the only way
I could defend myself was to have 72
classified documents Declassified and so
we pored through 15 or 20,000 classified
documents we found 72 that we believed
proved my innocence and we made seventy
two separate motions to the court to
order these documents to be declassified
we blocked off two days two full
eight-hour days in order to argue our
case so we walked into the courtroom and
before we even sat down in the chairs
the judge said let me save everybody
some time I'm denying all 72 of these
motions we were in and out in a few
minutes and on the way out
my attorney turned to me and said we
have no defense
if she won't let us have these documents
we simply can't defend you I said so
what do I do and he said we take a plea
Jeffrey sterling went through the same
thing he ended up going all the way to
trial all the way to a jury decision
without the ability to defend himself
Chelsea Manning the same thing so that's
why you end up looking at these
draconian sentences of 30 and 35 and 45
years you just don't have any way to win
yes thank you and now we have heard this
night different cases and all I related
to human rights expression of freedom
and so on either directly the artists
who are persecuted or ever as you were
you are telling about the the the the
thing thing is you know in in court
where which makes it difficult to defend
what an ordinary citizen would would
call the human right now there is an
international organization Amnesty
International and I wonder why it has
not been mentioned one time is it
because it's this international
organization is so weak or is it sort of
bought by the power the government in
power what is the reason or is it just I
don't know just not of any importance
why didn't you mention Amnesty
International thank you thank you for
that question
I begged Amnesty International to
release even a one-sentence statement
about my case I I wrote to MSD
headquarters in London and several
I wrote to Zeke Johnson the the director
of Amnesty International USA who was
kind enough to send me a subscription to
The New Yorker magazine along with a
letter saying I'm sorry but they don't
want to have anything to do with your
case and after about a year I got tired
of begging I got zero help from Amnesty
International nothing
can I just add to that as well exactly
the same experience after shayla's
conviction I went with them our lawyer
who was the head of the equivalent to
the ACLU in the UK to argue that amnesty
in London should declare David to be the
first political prisoner in the UK in
the UK's history I think a lot with
modern history and we won that argument
and the political committee that was
listening to have agreed and recommended
he should be but then it was stamped on
from a great height by the controlling
committee so yeah I perfectly understand
where you're coming from with that and
yeah it can we work with Amnesty some
sense I think I might mention them once
and I know some of the critique and we
were aware of the human rights movement
of course is this bureaucratization over
time it came out they were going to
depending on when this whole movement
right involved and now those big
organizations they are huge
bureaucracies with a lot of rules a lot
of lawyers everything goes up the chain
down the chain several times before they
say anything and of course when they
then say something it's verified and
it's like credible in many many ways but
it also makes them very inflexible and
taking up cases that are a little odd
like they are big bureaucracies by now
which I think the best intentions but
that is the limitation of the human
rights regime so to say I think so the
next time you all turn to us was the one
network Germany because we do have we
managed to set up a legal aid fund which
may provide professional advice to you
before you go public if you want to go
public
as John mentioned it's always better to
ask two for two professional help
especially with a complicated German
situation where there is no
whistleblower protection law at all so
our our flier is and the possibility is
to check in with us waiting for you at
the desk at the entrance desk and we
would be pleased if many of you would
make that decision and support us and I
think that Yanis is telling me that I
should wrap up this part of our event
and let me quickly say and before she
does it and let me quickly say that I
have the feeling that we have to be
grateful for what whistleblowers for
what we and the civil society that is
the civil society what we have learned
from widowhood
what we are still learning from them
from those being here and from those who
are not here and all the others who blew
the whistle because that gives us the
possibility to act and decide upon what
we then know speaking and now speaking
you we're speaking about the US and the
UK and I must say Germany we have pretty
much the same problems with the lowers
are not or even less protected in the UK
as in the u.s. at least last year we
have also passed several so-called
security laws that's the new speak I
realized that Annie is righteously
speaking of secrecy laws and whereas in
Germany they are called security laws so
we have passed the we have passed
several security last laws and
the parliamentary control of the
executive of the military and the secret
agencies secret services is insufficient
- and we know attempts to intimidate the
press - so let us not accept that and to
say it in Norman Solomon's word the
other day he said let's be a pain in the
neck he said let's be a pain in the neck
and let's publish everything the public
has a right to know and let's not forget
to ask why is that secret why the first
question to ask we have the human right
the freedom of its present as the
freedom of speech and the freedom of the
press and let's ask why is that secret
in the first place and not try to
legitimize why we speak out and most of
all and please keep in mind what Hannah
Adam the philosopher or the social
scientists on an errand has said nobody
has the right to obey
[Applause]
I just want to conclude but I don't want
to give you my back and I wanted to
thank you very much for this great panel
and also this great moderation and a
degree so and so I just wanted to
mention the people that curvy arrow so
that we can stay a bit longer
and use the bar so if you still have
energy please stay with us and also I
wanted to say remember to buy the book
of John that's even signed personally so
that is really a unique piece and I
finally also wanted to thank other
people of the team that I didn't think
Hank yes of course I wanted to thank the
theme of the Gruner salon that helped us
a lot with the technology with the cash
desk and also with the bass and the
Jonas Frankie that did a great visual
design that we saw at the event there
are photo cream crew that's documenting
our video and so much meet the
photographer and so high oppa we will
meet soon and you can also follow us
later on our TV see if you want to
subscribe the newsletter that is the
paper at the axis so now these little
technicalities and I want to thank again
all the great speaker bin with us today
and the public for saying goes on TV so
late thank you
[Applause]
thank you most of all